Anil Kumar, PhD (US Permanent Resident)

MS B262, Theoretical Division, Los Alamos National Laboratory, Los Alamos, NM 87545 anilk@lanl.gov anil5784@gmail.com 505-709-7714

Homepage: https://www.linkedin.com/in/anil5784/ **Google Scholar**: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=YMeExPwAAAAJ&hl=en

Profile Summary

Over ten years of research experience in computational materials modeling, data science and statistical analysis. Hands-on experience in programming in Python, R, Fortran, C/C++ and performing mathematical and statistical analysis, data mining and machine learning. Excellent interpersonal, oral and written communication skills, ability to quickly learn new tools and techniques to solve problems.

Professional Experience

- Research Associate, Los Alamos National Laboratory (09/2013-Present): Machine learning,
 Deep learning, Materials informatics, Data mining, Statistical analysis and prediction to discover new
 materials with targeted property, Microstructure reconstruction of polycrystal materials from X-ray
 diffraction images, Structure-properties relationship
- Postdoctoral Research Associate, Rutgers University (09/2010-08/2013): Materials modeling and simulations, Data analysis and visualization, Scientific presentations and publications
- **Graduate Research Assistant, JNCASR, Bangalore** (08/2005-08/2010): Development of materials modeling simulation programs, Data analysis /visualization, Presentation and publications.
- **Summer Intern, General Electric, Bangalore** (06/2009-08/2009): Finite Element Modeling of metal/oxide interface to enhance conductivity at interface and understand oxygen diffusivity in metals

Education

- PhD in Physics (2010): Jawaharlal Nehru Center for Advanced Scientific Research, Bangalore, India
- MSc in Physics (2005): Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi, India
- BSc in Physics, Mathematics and Computer Science (2003): Gorakhpur University, Gorakhpur, India

Programming and Data Science Skills

- Python, R, Fortran, C/C++
- Numpy, Scipy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn
- Scikit-learn, Keras, Tensorflow
- Big Data, Hadoop Ecosystem
- MapReduce and Apache Spark
- SQL/PostgreSQL

- Data Analysis, Machine Learning, Deep Learning
- Statistical Analysis and Uncertainty Quantification
- Recommender Systems, NLP
- Classification and Regression Analysis
- HPC, AWS, Cloud computing
- Mathematica, Matlab, MS Office, Latex

Computational Materials Modeling/Physics Skills

- Multiscale Modeling, Atomistic Simulations (MD/MC), Density Functional Theory
- First-principles Modeling and Simulations of Metals and Alloys, Structure-Property Relationship
- First-principles DFT Software: VASP, Quantum Espresso, Abinit, Siesta
- Molecular Dynamics Software: LAMMPS, Gromacs, NAMD, FERAM, Materials Studio
- Considerable domain knowledge of Physics and Materials Science

Transferable and Soft Skills

- Critical thinking, Problem solver, Attention to details, excellent time/project managements skills
- Expertise in preparing technical reports, publications and presentations
- Team Player: Enjoy working with people of different backgrounds and interests